<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="./_c74_ref.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<c74object name="nw.grainstream~" module="msp" category="LowkeyNW, MSP Sampling">

	<digest>
		Generate grains at a given frequency
	</digest>
	
	<description>
		Outputs a stream of grains at a given frequency in Hertz, and without any silence between the consecutive grain onsets. 
		This method can produce audio output similar to <o>wave~</o>, but with granular-specific controls and features such as windowing.  
		The sound source and window shape used by this object for grain production must each loaded into the <o>buffer~</o> objects specified by two required arguments.
	</description>
	
	<!--METADATA-->
	<metadatalist>
		<metadata name="author">Nathan Wolek</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">LowkeyNW</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">Audio</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">Sampling</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">64-bit</metadata>
	</metadatalist>
	
	<!--INLETS-->
	<inletlist>
		<inlet id="0" type="signal">
			<digest>Frequency in Hz. Grains are produced at this rate.</digest>
		</inlet>
		<inlet id="1" type="signal/float">
			<digest>Sound offset in ms. Where to start reading the sound buffer.</digest>
		</inlet>
		<inlet id="2" type="signal/float">
			<digest>Sample increment. Effects perceived pitch, 1.0 = unchanged.</digest>
		</inlet>
		<inlet id="3" type="signal/float">
			<digest>Gain multiplier, 1.0 = unchanged.</digest>
		</inlet>
	</inletlist>

	<!--OUTLETS-->
	<outletlist>
		<outlet id="0" type="signal">
			<digest>Audio signal: audio channel 1</digest>
		</outlet>
		<outlet id="1" type="signal">
			<digest>Audio signal: audio channel 2</digest>
		</outlet>
		<outlet id="2" type="signal">
			<digest>Audio signal: sample count since playback started. -1 = no playback.</digest>
		</outlet>
	</outletlist>
	
	<!--ARGUMENTS-->
	<objarglist>
		<objarg name="sound-buffer-name" optional="0" type="symbol">
			<digest>
				Sound buffer object name
			</digest>
			<description>
				The first argument names the <o>buffer~</o> object whose sample memory contains a source source used by this object for grain production.
				For more information about how this sample memory is handled, see documentation for the <m>setSound</m> message.
			</description>
		</objarg>
		<objarg name="window-buffer-name" optional="0" type="symbol">
			<digest>
				Window buffer object name
			</digest>
			<description>
				The second argument names the <o>buffer~</o> object whose sample memory contains a window function used by this object for grain production.
				For more information about how this sample memory is handled, see documentation for the <m>setWin</m> message.
			</description>
		</objarg>
	</objarglist>
	
	<!--MESSAGES-->
	<methodlist>
		<method name="int">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="parameter-settings" optional="0" type="int" />
			</arglist>
			<digest>
				Function depends on inlet
			</digest>
			<description>
				Numbers can be used instead of signal objects to control sound offset, grain duration, sample increment and gain multiplier. If a <m>signal</m> is also connected to the inlet, <m>float</m> and <m>int</m> messages will be ignored.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="float">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="parameter-settings" optional="0" type="float" />
			</arglist>
			<digest>
				Function depends on inlet
			</digest>
			<description>
				Numbers can be used instead of signal objects to control sound offset, grain duration, sample increment and gain multiplier. If a <m>signal</m> is also connected to the inlet, <m>float</m> and <m>int</m> messages will be ignored.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="signal">
			<arglist />
			<digest>
				Function depends on inlet
			</digest>
			<description>
				After a grain begins sounding, changes received by the following inlets will be deferred to the start of the next grain:
				<br />
				<br />
				In inlet 1: Defines the frequency of grain production in Hertz.
				This value can be thought of as the inverse of duration, with no silence between grains.
				The absolute value of any negative numbers are used to prevent buffer overrun errors.
				If backward playback is desired, use the <b>reverse 1</b> message.
				In addition, values less than 0.05 Hz will be ignored because of the potential for excessively long grain durations. 
				<br />
				<br />
				In inlet 2: Defines the offset in milliseconds from the beginning of the sound <o>buffer~</o> where processing should start reading for grain production. 
				<br />
				<br />
				In inlet 3: Defines the sample increment used while reading sound <o>buffer~</o> contents.
				This changes the perceived pitch, with 1.0 resulting in normal playback.
				The absolute value of any negative numbers are used to prevent buffer overrun errors.
				If backward playback is desired, use the <b>reverse 1</b> message.
				<br />
				<br />
				In inlet 4: Defines the gain multiplier.
				All values within a grain will be scaled by this number, with 1.0 resulting in no change.
				<br />
				<br />
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="setSound">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="sound-buffer-name" optional="0" type="symbol" />
			</arglist>
			<digest>
				Set the name of the sound <o>buffer~</o> used for grain production.
			</digest>
			<description>
				The word <m>setSound</m>, followed by the name of a <o>buffer~</o> object, uses that object's sample memory as source sound for grain production.
				Note that this <o>buffer~</o> object can have up to 2 channels.
				In the case of 1 channel (mono), the sound produced by both the first and second outlets will be the same.
				In the case of 2 channels (stereo), the first outlet will playback sound from the first channel (left) and the second outlet will playback sound from the second channel (right).
				Changes sent by the <m>setSound</m> message are deferred to the start of the next grain. 
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="setWin">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="window-buffer-name" optional="0" type="symbol" />
			</arglist>
			<digest>
				Set the name of the window <o>buffer~</o> used for grain production.
			</digest>
			<description>
				The word <m>setWin</m>, followed by the name of a <o>buffer~</o> object, uses that object's sample memory as a window function for grain production.
				Note that this <o>buffer~</o> object can only have 1 channel (mono).
				Changes sent by the <m>setWin</m> message are deferred to the start of the next grain. 
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="reverse">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="reverse" optional="0" type="int" />
			</arglist>
			<digest>
				Read the defined <o>buffer~</o> segment backwards. Default is off.
			</digest>
			<description>
				A <m>reverse 1</m> message will play the defined <o>buffer~</o> segment backwards.
				A <m>reverse 0</m> message will play the defined <o>buffer~</o> segment forward.
				Changes sent by the <m>reverse</m> message are deferred to the start of the next segment. 
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="sndInterp">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="sound-interpolation" optional="0" type="int" />
			</arglist>
			<digest>
				Use interpolation while reading samples from the sound <o>buffer~</o>. Default is on.
			</digest>
			<description>
				An <m>sndInterp 1</m> message will use linear interpolation while reading from the sound <o>buffer~</o>.
				An <m>sndInterp 0</m> message will use no interpolation while reading from the sound <o>buffer~</o>.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="winInterp">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="window-interpolation" optional="0" type="int" />
			</arglist>
			<digest>
				Use interpolation while reading samples from the window <o>buffer~</o>. Default is on.
			</digest>
			<description>
				An <m>winInterp 1</m> message will use linear interpolation while reading from the window <o>buffer~</o>.
				An <m>winInterp 0</m> message will use no interpolation while reading from the window <o>buffer~</o>.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="getinfo">
			<arglist />
			<digest>
				Post information about object to Max window
			</digest>
			<description>
				Retrieves basic information about the object author and when the object was last updated. Date can be used to identify different versions of the objects in circulation.
			</description>
		</method>
	</methodlist>
	
	<!--SEEALSO-->
	<seealsolist>
		<seealso name="buffer~"/>
		<seealso name="stutter~"/>
		<seealso name="wave~" />
		<seealso name="index~" />
	</seealsolist>
	
</c74object>